<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>State-maxims, or, Certain dangerous positions, destructive to the very natural right and liberty of mankind. Laid down in a book entituled, The grounds of government and obedience; by Tho. White Gent. / Discussed, and both by Scripture and reason confuted, by Will Ball Esq;</title>
            <author>Ball, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E886_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E886[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>State-maxims, or, Certain dangerous positions, destructive to the very natural right and liberty of mankind. Laid down in a book entituled, The grounds of government and obedience; by Tho. White Gent. / Discussed, and both by Scripture and reason confuted, by Will Ball Esq;</title>
                  <author>Ball, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Dawson, for T. Brewster at the three Bibles at the west-end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655 [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: White, Thomas.  The grounds of obedience and government.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 5th"; 5 in imprint date written over with "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>White, Thomas, 1593-1676. --  Grounds of obedience and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168405:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>STATE-MAXIMS, OR, CERTAIN DANGEROUS POSITIONS, Deſtructive to the very natural Right and Liberty of Mankind.</p>
            <p>Laid down in a Book entituled, <hi>The Grounds of Government and Obedience;</hi> By THO. WHITE Gent.</p>
            <p>Diſcuſſed, and both by Scripture and Reaſon confuted, by WILL BALL Eſq;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Dawſon,</hi> for T. <hi>Brewſter</hi> at the three Bibles at the Weſt-End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168405:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168405:2"/>
            <head>The Authors Motives <hi>inducing him to write and publiſh this ſmall Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, It hath in almoſt all Ages been too much the Practice of ſome able Wits, to advance a boundleſs <hi>Interest</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates; as if that <hi>Majestas Imperii</hi> (not <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Populi)</hi> were the adequate, yea, total ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and end of all humane Government: by meanes whereof Oppreſsion hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread, and Tyranny under yoaked many of the greateſt and moſt flouriſhing Nations on the Earth. But ſuch men (who have ſometimes been <hi>Mercurialists,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Martialiſts,</hi> ſometimes both) might be term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Humani Generis inimici,</hi> for that either in hopes of their own Preferments, or Applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they expoſed to ſale (I might ſay ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack) the Natural, or innate Liberty of all mankind.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There have alwayes been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (too many) churliſh ſtubborn Perſons, who have hated and oppoſed <hi>Regular</hi> Civil
<pb facs="tcp:168405:3"/> Government (although Prudent and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate) even as exorbitant Tyranny, and boundleſs Potency; but ſuch may be term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bruit beaſts of the wilderneſs, who by <hi>Irregular</hi> Licenciouſneſs would deſtroy the well ordered and cultivated Proprieties of all civilized People.</p>
            <p>Now, the Author of this ſmall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Treatiſe, was moved to write and publiſh the ſame, to ſatisfie (if it may be) both the one and the other by candid and concluding Reaſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILL. BALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168405:3"/>
            <head>OBSERVATIONS Upon a Book intituled, <hi>The Grounds of Obedience and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> Printed 1655.</head>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATION 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vpon the ſixt Ground,</hi> Touching Right, or Due.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have peruſed a Book intituled, <hi>The Grounds of Obedience, and Government,</hi> written by <hi>Thomas White</hi> Gentleman; wherein <hi>ſelf-end or intereſt</hi> is greatly implyed, and though the Author ſeem <hi>to diſlike blind obedience,</hi> yet he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth to <hi>enſlave free men under the Bondage of Boundleſs Government, or rather Governors.</hi> I ſhall inſtance and inſiſt upon the <hi>Poſitions of the ſixt Ground,</hi> not the firſt, but the fitteſt to begin withall.</p>
               <p>The words are theſe: <hi>We ought therefore to know, that a man, conſidered in pure nature, looks on all other things, men, and beaſts, and inſenſible creatures, as his</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168405:4"/> 
                  <hi>ſubjects to work on; his onely Rule being Reaſon, which takes nothing to be good, but what is good to himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will examine this <hi>Poſition,</hi> firſt according to the Rule of the Creator, and then according to the Rule of the Creature: All School-men agree, that <hi>GOD worketh all things for himſelf,</hi> but they do not all agree touching the <hi>formal Reaſon,</hi> why he ſo worketh: Some hold that GOD worketh meerly becauſe he will ſo; but this is groſs, to ſay, that God <hi>meerly willeth,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note place="margin">Non vult Deus quia vult, ſed quia velle ſapit.</note> the <hi>Dictamen</hi> of his Divine Knowledge; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. <hi>Whom he foreknew he alſo predeſtinated:</hi> as for that touching <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> cap. 9. it onely ſheweth, that GODS eternal Decree precedeth matter of Fact, not that his eternal Decree precedeth his Divine Knowledge. Others hold, that GOD worketh to the end he may manifeſt his Attributes; but this is to ſay, that GOD hath a ſelf-end diſſonant to his Greatneſs and Goodneſs. For what doth the manifeſtation of Attributes add to GOD, whoſe Greatneſs and Glory conſiſteth in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Octjectum creationis eſt Bonitas ipſa Divina ut communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis</hi> partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pative. Gen. 1. 4. 10. 12, &amp;c. <hi>Potuit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ulterius communicare</hi> Participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Bonitatem creaturis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilibus, Deo tamen viſa eſt ſufficieus Exiſtenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atio.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſelf-Being,</hi> not in <hi>ſelf-ends?</hi> Nor can an <hi>extrinſecal end</hi> be the adequate object of the infinite Greatneſs and Goodneſs of GOD. Others therefore ſay, (and that more truly) that GOD worketh to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>his Goodneſs</hi> ſeverally, and this is agreeable as to the Action of Creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 4. 10. &amp;c. ſo to the myſtery of Incarnation, of which it is ſaid; <hi>John</hi> 3. 16. <hi>So God loved the world, that he gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son:</hi> Now if GOD work to communicate his Goodneſs, ought not man, <hi>conſidered in pure nature,</hi> work (what he may) to communicate good to others, and not meerly or wholly to himſelf? Ought he not alſo by the Rule of Reaſon to take that for good, which is good to others, as well as to himſelf? Ought
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168405:4"/> not the reaſonable creature, <hi>conſidered in pure nature,</hi> to follow the Rule of his Creator: Moreover, can a man, <hi>conſidered in pure nature,</hi> (and conſequently in prudent Reaſon) <hi>look on all other things, men, and beaſts, and inſenſible Creatures, as his ſubjects to work on?</hi> Is there not <hi>ſubjectum per quod,</hi> which is <hi>the meanes whereby,</hi> and <hi>ſubjectum ad quod,</hi> which is <hi>the adaequate Term,</hi> as well as <hi>ſubjectum quod</hi> the ſubject or ground whereon to work? Certainly prudent Reaſon dictates ſo. When GOD created <hi>Eve</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Let us make him an help, ut ſubjectum per quod;</hi> he ſaid not, let us make him a ſubject to work upon, as <hi>ſubjectum quod:</hi> And if <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity had perſevered in the ſtate of Innocence, doubtleſs he and they had educated their children (being the <hi>adequate Terms</hi> of their Propagation, or Generation) in holy contemplation, and ſome bodily employment (for certainly he and they ſhould not have lived idly, albeit <note place="margin">This may be gathered from the 2. of Gen. v. 5.</note> their employment, or work, ſhould have been no toil, or tediouſneſs unto them) ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould not have looked on any of his Poſterity in the ſtate of Innocence, or <hi>in pure nature,</hi> as <hi>a ſubject to work on,</hi> but rather <hi>as a ſubject to work for, or to:</hi> (other creatures peradventure he might have looked on as ſubjects to work on) wherefore it is improper, yea, dangerous to ſay, <hi>that a man, conſidered in pure nature, looketh on men (as well as Beaſts, and inſenſible creatures) as his ſubjects to work on;</hi> it is the way to make men wholly ſelf-ended, and to vilifie others.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Section, or Ground, Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſaith; <hi>It is true, there is an inclination in man, from Reaſon, to do another any good I can</hi> (ſo it is printed) <hi>without my own prejudice, and to have a deſire to keep Peace with all men. But if I do not, it follows not that I wrong him,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168405:5"/> 
                  <hi>even though I do him harm, or ſeek his ruine: But I wrong my ſelf, nature binding me to make my carriage to every one Rational, and becomming a man, for he is no otherwiſe to me than a piece of cloth or wood, which I cut and ſhape after my own will, ſittingly for my uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would know of any Rational man, whether pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Reaſon (even as Religion) do not dictate this of St. <hi>Luke, cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 31. <hi>And as ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye alſo to them likewiſe?</hi> Certainly prudent Reaſon, no way over-byaſſed by pernicious will, dictates, that <hi>good is ſpecified of, or by an entire cauſe,</hi> an entire object, an entire end; and therefore prudent Reaſon dictates alſo, that GOD is to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for his excellency, not for our own ends (as the Devil falſly alleadged againſt <hi>Job)</hi> and that man, or all mankind is to be loved for GOD's ſake, becauſe he hath dignified him with a Rational ſoul, and not meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the uſe one man hath of another: ſo that, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to prudent Reaſon, I ſhould not onely have an <hi>inclination</hi> to do another man what good I can, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mine own prejudice, but even an <hi>Actual Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of what good I may prudently without my own wrong, if he will accept thereof; however I ought no way to wrong him, <hi>but to do unto him, being my equal in nature, as I would have him do unto me:</hi> would I have him do unto me good, if I ſtood in need there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, albeit I were not able to require it? I ought to do the like. Would I have him <hi>do me no harm, nor ſeek my ruine,</hi> by depriving me of my natural liberty, <hi>which is an individual power of what is lawful,</hi> or by depriving me of my National propriety, <hi>which is a legal Relation to a temporal benefit?</hi> I ought not to do it to him. Would I have him <hi>eſteem me no otherwiſe than a peice of cloth, or wood, and to cut or ſhape me after</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168405:5"/> 
                  <hi>his will, fittingly for his uſe?</hi> Why then ſhould I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him no otherwiſe, or ſhape him according to my uſe, unleſs he freely give his conſent thereunto? Bruit beaſts have a ſenſible eſtimation of thoſe which are of their own <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or kind; kill but an hog, and thoſe of his own kind ſhall approach ſhewing their diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent by their grunting, and endeavouring what they may to reſcue their fellow-creature: Beaſts of prey, although they fall out about their prey, will not prey upon thoſe of their kind: Shall a man then prey on another <hi>by doing him harm, or ſeeking his ruine, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralling him againſt his will,</hi> without any Offence or Demerit on his part? Certainly this is ſo little ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to manhood, that it is worſe than beſtial; and Mr. <hi>White</hi> his Poſitions before recited are ſo deſtructive to humane ſociety, that he may ſeem to ſome to be an <hi>Athenian Timon,</hi> an hater of mankind.</p>
               <p>And now I think it not amiſs to deliver ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what concerning <hi>Right or Due.</hi> I frame therefore theſe Definitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jus eſt Regula rectae Rationi undequa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Right, or rather righteous dealing, is a Rule every way agreeing to right Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex eſt norma Politica, Protectioni &amp; Ordini conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Law is a Politick Rule convenient to Protection, and Order.</p>
               <p>By the firſt every one (having the uſe of Reaſon) is tyed to do what good he may to another (not prejudicing himſelf) and <hi>to do as he would be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the firſt alſo every man hath a natural or Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinal Propriety to a livelihood: for <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168405:6"/> had a Natural or Rational Propriety of the Garden <note place="margin">Although Paradiſe in Reſpect of the Garden it ſelf, was (in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of many) but ſmall, yet in Reſpect of its extent it may ſeem to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the goodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of <hi>Aſia;</hi> more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over GOD could have enlarged it, in caſe the Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> had perſevered in Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</note> of <hi>Eden,</hi> or Paradiſe; GOD excepting, by way of Prohibition, the <hi>Tree of good and evil:</hi> which Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made a Propriety, ſhewing what was theirs, what not: and doubtleſs, had their Poſterity perſevered in the ſtate of Innocency, they had had Propriety of Food (peradventure of Rayment and Ornament) Regulated by right Reaſon without confuſion, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, &amp; probably Paradiſe might have been propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to the children of Innocence, as was the Land of Promiſe to the Children of Iſrael: but ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> natural or Rational Propriety fals under Legal, and Individual, of which in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>By this Rule likewiſe the will of one man (having the uſe of Reaſon) is not ſubject to the will of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>any further than he ſubjugateth himſelf:</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>conjugal ſubjection</hi> was pronounced againſt <hi>Eve, Gen.</hi> 3. 16. as part of her puniſhment for her diſobedience toward GOD (which ſubjection was <note place="margin">As conjugal ſubjection was from <hi>Eve</hi> Tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to her Sex, ſo from her <hi>Potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is to ſay, that the will of one man might <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> (not <hi>naturally)</hi> be <hi>ſubject</hi> to the will of another) was Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to all mankind: even as was the <hi>Original</hi> Averſion of the mind from GOD, and Rebellion of the fleſh againſt the ſpirit Traduced from <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>traduced to her</hi> Sex) yet neither men, nor women (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal ſubjection excepted) are <hi>De Jure naturali,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject one to another; being by nature equal, as are the Angels in heaven, amongſt whom there is onely a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority of excellence, no ſoveraignity of Power one over another, for that would not be agreeable to their <hi>free,</hi> compleat, and continual fruition of God in the Beatitude of Glory, the moſt perfect of all ſtates. But ſome it may be will ſay, that Children by the Law of Nature are ſubject to their Parents: In which, I ſay, there may be a miſtake; for if <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had perſevered in the ſtate of Innocence, there had <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168405:6"/> been ſuch an <hi>Harmony</hi> in nature, that the Child ſhould not have offended the Parent, and then there had been no cauſe of ſoveraignty, and ſubjection, but onely of Paternal Love, and filial Honor, ſo that Children are not ſubject to their Parents by the rule of <hi>pure</hi> nature, but in regard, or reſpect of <hi>depraved</hi> nature: Moreover in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> it is written, <hi>Honor thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> as the Inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal cauſes of natural Being; it is not written, be wholly ſubject to thy father and mother, as to <hi>ſoveraign Lords</hi> over thee. We know that ſons and daughters (who have attained to the mature Ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">Subjectio Filialis eſt tantum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentia Naturalis erga Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in Finem debitum.</note> of convenient Reaſon) may not onely in matters of Religion, but even in the Latitude of morality, with due Reverence admoniſh, and reprehend, yea, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally oppoſe their Parents.</p>
               <p>In <hi>England,</hi> when any one under age is bound Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice, it is ſpecified, or ſignified in the Indenture, that he or ſhe were ſo bound, not onely by conſent of their Parents or Friends, but by their own conſent, to ſignifie, that he or ſhew was not bound <hi>but by their own voluntary ſubmiſsion.</hi> Thus much of the firſt Rule.</p>
               <p>By the ſecond Politick Rule of Law, men have their ſeveral Proprieties of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally;</hi> ſometimes by way of <hi>Legal</hi> Poſſeſſion, which is <hi>facultas Poſitiva aliquod bonum mundanum comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens;</hi> a Poſitive faculty comprehending a worldly Good: So it is of Houſe, Land, &amp;c. ſometimes by way of Legal uſe, which is <hi>Applicatio Poſitiva alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Boni mundani;</hi> a Poſitive Application of ſome worldly Good: and ſo it is of money and other Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels which a man applieth to his uſe: Sometimes alſo by way of <hi>Legal</hi> Office, which is <hi>Poteſtatis alicujus in finem debitum Referentia Poſitiva,</hi> a Poſitive Reference
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168405:7"/> (or Relation) of ſome Power to a due end; ſuch is the nature of all Offices from that of a King, to that of a Conſtable. Now whoſoever ſhall <hi>digreſs</hi> from either of theſe Rules (much more whoſoever ſhall Actually <hi>Tranſgreſs) by endeavouring to harm, or ſeeking the Ruine of another</hi> in any of the Particulars forementioned, doth <hi>deviate</hi> from <hi>right Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>unmans</hi> himſelf by becomming unhumane.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>OBSERVATION II. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Upon the eight Ground, touching</hi> the Authority given to an abſolute Governour: <hi>upon the ninth Ground, touching</hi> the lawfulneſs of ſlavery; <hi>and alſo upon the eleventh Ground, touching</hi> the quality, and Rational Power of a ſupream Governour.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN this Obſervation I ſhall be enforced to recite much of what Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſtates by way of Poſitive aſſertion, to ravel out what he hath knit, or rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duly knotted together.</p>
               <p>He ſaith <hi>(Ground</hi> 8.) <hi>That the People, as far as they have renounced their own will, ſo farre they have no power left in them to contradict, or reſiſt the Orders of the Magiſtracy.</hi> I ſay, <hi>So far as the People have ſubmitted their wils: for ſince this Power is in the Magiſtrate in vertue of their wils, it cannot extend far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Peoples promiſe: ſo that if the People bind their Magiſtrate to certain Laws and Limits; he hath</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:168405:7"/> 
                  <hi>no right to tranſgreſs ſuch Laws, nor extend himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the prefixed Limits, by his inſtallation, and the original Power given him: But above all he cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of one chip or diſpence in one the leaſt Law, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than he apprehends it as fit and neceſſary to the good of the Common-wealth:</hi> Here is to be obſerved, that the People are not ſubject <hi>but ſo far as they have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their wils;</hi> that the Magiſtrate <hi>hath no right to tranſgreſs ſuch Laws, or extend himſelf beyond the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits prefixed to him:</hi> So then, if the People bind their ſupream Magiſtrate (by Oath, and Promiſe, or ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) not to make, or repeal Laws, nor impoſe Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or the like, without their conſent given by their <hi>Truſtees,</hi> Deputies, or Delegates, he hath no Right to do any of them: yea! but ſaith he; <hi>In caſe the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate apprehend it fit and neceſſary to the good of the Common-wealth, he may in ſomewhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence touching Law:</hi> Verily Mr. <hi>White</hi> his magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Licence is far worſe than Poetical Licence, for this onely maketh words long, or ſhort, but that of his maketh Laws long, or ſhort, at the <hi>Magiſtrates appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I demand, whether the ſupream Magiſtrate appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending ſomewhat <hi>good for the Common-wealth,</hi> may not miſtake? Whether he may not meerly <hi>pretend good to the Common-wealth</hi> (as even all ſelf-ended Potentates do) and intend it not? if ſo; why ſhould a People be ſubject to his frail, or poſſibly, yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably <hi>erring apprehenſion, or doubtful intention?</hi> Should they have thought it fit; they would have ſubmitted their wils, and conferred ſuch Authority up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſupream Magiſtrate at his inſtalment; not thinking it fit, it is clear they <hi>Reſerved (for what is</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:168405:8"/> 
                  <hi>not conferred is Reſerved)</hi> to themſelves cheifly the power of judging what is <hi>fit and neceſſary to the good of the Common-wealth:</hi> So that the ſupream Magiſtrate (limited as aforeſaid) hath no right to diſpence with, or <hi>in the leaſt Law, to nul or abrogate it;</hi> but he hath onely Power to diſpenſe with matter of execution of the Law in ſome caſes; as to pardon or exempt a Delinquent from Puniſhment, where the Parties for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer merits, or hope of future Behaviour, may ſeem to counterpoiſe his demerits. Farthermore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it dangerous to any People, who deſire to live under <hi>a certain Rule of Law,</hi> to be ſubject to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrates <hi>uncertain apprehenſion, and Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in permitting him (upon any pretence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) <hi>to diſpence in the leaſt Law</hi> generally beneficial; <note place="margin">The ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may diſpenſe with a Law prejudicial to many, or ſome, and beneficial to none but himſelf.</note> for if he find that he may make ruptures in the <hi>leſſer,</hi> he will not want pretences upon ſeeming (peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture probable) Reaſons to break through as many (though of greater importance) as ſtand in his way, or ſeem inconvenient unto him. It is ſaid by a great Politician, that tell a good Prince that he may do what he liſt, <hi>ex optimo fit peſsimus,</hi> he ſoon becomes from good the worſt of all; if he begin <hi>to tread upon one Law,</hi> he will proceed <hi>to trample upon others at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome will ſay, there may be ſuch an exigency in Affairs of the Common-wealth, that the ſupream Governour may be enforced to do ſomething diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from Law; as if a ſudden invaſion happen, he may be conſtrained to levy forces, and raiſe money for defence of the Common-wealth, without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and explicite conſent of the People, or their Truſtees.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168405:8"/>
               <p> I anſwer; That this is a thing ſeldom not foreſeen, ſo that he may have time enough to require the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples conſent: but if ſuch a thing ſhould unuſually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, he then by raiſing of forces, and money <hi>for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive War, doth not diſpenſe with Law,</hi> but onely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſeth with matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> agreeable to the end of <hi>Law,</hi> which is <hi>ſalus Populi.</hi> Otherwiſe it is when (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the People, or their Truſtees) he le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies forces and raiſes money <hi>for Offenſive War,</hi> for <note place="margin">An <hi>unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate may make war without the conſent of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: ſo alſo may a <hi>limited</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, if not limited to matter of Peace and War.</note> then (if he be limited as aforeſaid) he doth a thing different from Law in <hi>propriam Majeſtatem</hi> to advance (it may be) his own Greatneſs, and to engage the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in war without their conſent and approbation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (by their Truſtees, or Delegates) touching the <hi>cauſe</hi> why, and <hi>end</hi> what, and <hi>meanes</hi> how.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now deſcend from this Diſcourſe to that of <hi>ſlavery: Whether</hi> (as Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath it, Page 59.) <hi>a whole Nation may voluntarily ſubmit it ſelf to a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by which it ſhall have nothing of its own, nor be able to deſerve or get any thing; but be entirely at the diſpoſition of the Magiſtrate it chuſeth, without right or propriety:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, They may, though imprudently, and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, not ſutable to the nature of reaſonable men, but bruit beaſts. Yet I ſay, that <hi>ſuch their ſlaviſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> doth not, nor cannot enſlave their Poſterity, no more than the Bond of a Father, who hath no Power to ſell his Land, doth oblige the Son to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Fathers covenants: for a People cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive their Poſterity of their <hi>natural Right,</hi> which is (amongſt other things) not to be farther ſubject than they ſubmit their wils; as I have before inſtanced, and as Mr. <hi>White</hi> granteth.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168405:9"/>
               <p> I but ſome will ſay, a Father (and conſequently a People) may deprive a Child of his inheritance, and why not of his Liberty or Freedom?</p>
               <p>I ſay, the caſe is not alike; for inheritance is <hi>Legall Poſitively,</hi> ſo that according to the Laws of ſome Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (though not altogether Rational) a Son may be deprived of his inheritance; but Liberty (ſuch as I inſtance) is <hi>natural inherently,</hi> ſo that a Father cannot deprive a Son of that, becauſe it is <hi>the Gift of GOD as the Author of Nature;</hi> nor conſequently one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration another, both in regard of its inherency in Nature, and priority by Nature before any written, or <hi>conditional Law.</hi> Wherefore I affirm, that not onely the Progeny of the <hi>Greeks</hi> (who are enſlaved by force) but alſo the Progeny of the <hi>Muſcovites,</hi> and ſuch like People (whoſe Predeceſſors enſlaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) may free themſelves from ſlavery, in caſe themſelves have not, or do not <hi>Actually</hi> by their own voluntary ſubmiſſion enſlave themſelves: Nor in ſo doing ſhould they oppoſe the <hi>direct end</hi> of Power, which is <hi>Dignitas Regularis in Ordinis, &amp; Protectionis conſervationem:</hi> a Regular Dignity to, or for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Order and Protection, according to that of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 6. but they ſhould onely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>indirect end</hi> of violation, or violence, which is <hi>Impetus irregularis in oppreſsionis, &amp; ſervitutis invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaris impoſitionem,</hi> an irregular force for impoſition of oppreſſion, and involuntary, or conſtrained ſlavery, deſtructive to <hi>natural inherent Right</hi> given by GOD, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now again revert and reflect upon the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and condition of the high or ſupream Magiſtrate, tyed, bound, or concluded by the <hi>Peoples Limitations.</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168405:9"/> Mr. <hi>White</hi> putteth the caſe (Ground 11. Page 83. &amp; 84.) <hi>When ſome great fault diſcovers it ſelf in the Limitations, and the end of Government is prejudiced by ſuch a defect; and nevertheleſs it is no doubt, but tis the intention of the People, or the Truſtees of the People, to bind their Magiſtrate to ſuch conditions; whether in ſuch a caſe, he be bound to his Orders, and Oath, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the duty of a wiſe and good man doth enfranchiſe him to do what is truly beſt for the People, though it be againſt their wils?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſeemeth to imply ſome difficulty in the queſtion, but I can find none: for if <hi>any great fault diſcover it ſelf in any Limitations</hi> (being matters ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally well prepondered and debated by the moſt prudent of the People, or their Truſtees) the high Magiſtrate may in convenient time convene the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees of the People, to whom he may propound, with whom he may debate, and by whom he may reform, <hi>ſuch fault in the Limitations</hi> (if any ſuch be) and no doubt but ſome of them will be as quick-ſighted as himſelf, and as willing to reform any fault for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good: but however he himſelf is ſtrictly tied <hi>to the obſervation of his Orders and Oath,</hi> by the Rule of Religion (if he have any) which teacheth, that <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Covenants are without fraud to be kept, Pſalm</hi> 14. Moreover the Apoſtle teacheth us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>That we ought not to do evil that good may come of it:</hi> how then may we <hi>falſifie an Oath</hi> for any humane end, or good? Farthermore Reaſon dictateth, that to do a Rational man <hi>good againſt his will,</hi> is not rationally good, becauſe I violate his will he eſteeming it no Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional good.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168405:10"/>
               <p> Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſaith (page 61.) <hi>But when I ſpeak of a Nation, methinks I ſpeak of Nature it ſelf:</hi> And me thinks when I ſpeak of the Truſtees of a Nation, I ſpeak of Reaſon it ſelf; who as they ought not, ſo they need not have any humane good enforced upon them, themſelves being an <hi>Epitome</hi> of all humane Reaſon to know, and proſecute or purſue any humane good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to themſelves, ſo that the <hi>high Magiſtrate</hi> doth them wrong, if he do them good againſt their wils.</p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſaith (page 88.) that <hi>he is intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to do for the common good:</hi> and then proceeds to ſay, <hi>He then of neceſsity muſt be falſe to his Oath, if he do not, according to his Truſt, act for the common good what he evidently ſees in a high degree to import it: further, becauſe we know, in moral buſineſſes, the end aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, is more principal than the meanes ordered to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt tell Mr. <hi>White,</hi> that (according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb) he runneth before his horſe to market: for a <hi>Limited</hi> high Magiſtrate, or Governour, <hi>is not intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do all good in general to a Common-wealth,</hi> but onely <hi>ſuch good</hi> as is comprehended <hi>in his Rules and limitations;</hi> even as a General of War is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted generally in all things touching War, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſuch affairs of War as are contained in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and Commiſſion; ſo the high Magiſtrate <hi>is not falſe to his Oath,</hi> if he obſerve his Limitations, but <hi>he is falſe to his Oath</hi> if be exceed them. In Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Government the People in many places Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to, or for their Truſtees, a joynt-power <hi>Juridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> or Law-making (being the greateſt <hi>ultimate end of their common good)</hi> and as they grant, ſo they tie and bind their high Magiſtrate by promiſe and oath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168405:10"/> to a Power <hi>Juritenent</hi> or Law-adminiſtring (being <hi>the greateſt meanes to the ultimate end)</hi> wherefore the <hi>cheifeſt end</hi> a Limited high Magiſtrate ſhould look upon (as comprehended within the ſphere of his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity) is <hi>the beſt means</hi> of Law-adminiſtring, leaving <hi>the ultimate end of Law-making or common good to the Truſtees of the People,</hi> and not to undertake what by his Rules and Limitations he is not intruſted with; leaſt he be eſteemed an Arbitrary Tyrant, or perfidious enemy to the People (though he intend real good) and be cenſured, or adjudged accordingly: for the Truſtees of the People <hi>(to whom Law-making and care of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good is cheifly referred by the People)</hi> may cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or judge an irregular, exorbitant or Tyrannical limited high Magiſtrate, and not onely depoſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place him, but condemn and puniſh him, as they ſhall think fit. The Reaſon is, becauſe the Limited Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Law-adminiſtring is ſubordinate to the General Power of Law-making, as is the meanes to the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment and preſervation of the end. Yet the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees of the People are not altogether unlimited (though ſome ſuppoſe otherwiſe) as I ſhall hereafter declare.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Gentleman ſaith (page 90.) <hi>How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promiſes do Divines and Lawyers pronounce null, though they were good and valid when they were made, by reaſon of the change of accidents following, which could not be foreſeen?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Gentleman muſt give me leave to tell him, that ſome ſubtle Caſuiſts, and crafty Lawyers, do <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſome promiſes null</hi> which ought to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and adjudged valid: indeed not any promiſe of any thing good and lawful <hi>ought to be pronounced or</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:168405:11"/> 
                  <hi>adjudged null,</hi> unleſs it be illegally obtained by force, forgery, or fraud; not through the Promiſers volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary neglect, or careleſs miſtake: wherefore <hi>he that giveth to another all that is in a Trunk</hi> [I inſtance the Gentleman's example, page 90.] <hi>wherein himſelf had put nothing but a Suit of Aparrel, and his ſervant without his knowledge had taken that out and put in bags of Gold in the ſame bulk;</hi> I ſay (that unleſs the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter can make it appear, that the ſervant did of purpoſe put into the Trunk the bags of Gold to defraud his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) the perſon to whom he gave the Trunk withal in it, ought to have and enjoy it; for it was <hi>caſus fortunae,</hi> or more Theologically, the providence of GOD pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the maſters careleſs neglect, who, if he knew that his ſervant had ſuch power committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as that he might put any thing in or out, ſhould prudently have fore-ſeen and over-ſeen it. In like manner, he that promiſeth <hi>abſolutely</hi> his <hi>Daughter in marriage to another, and afterwards the party is not found to be of ſuch competent means, as the father of the Daughter eſteemed him to be</hi> (I omit matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and manners, for thoſe being diſſembled may ſometimes alter the caſe) <hi>is for his part</hi> tied <hi>Jure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus civilis to perform his promiſe,</hi> for he might pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and carefully have looked into the parties means, before he had made an <hi>abſolute</hi> promiſe; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Daughter is free to diſſent, if ſhe have not <hi>abſolutely</hi> given her conſent. But neither theſe caſes of imprudence and negligence, nor that of <hi>Jephte,</hi> can give ſcope to a <hi>Limited</hi> high Magiſtrate for promiſe, or oath-breaking: for <hi>Jephte</hi> made a raſh and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vow, he ſhould have prudently conſidered what had been fit to ſacrifice to GOD, and not have raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168405:11"/> vowed to ſacrifice the firſt thing that met him from home, which caſually might have been one of his neighbours or ſervants, as it was his onely daughter; and therefore in the Opinion of ſolid Divines he ought rather to have broken his raſh vow, than to have ſacrificed his daughter: howbeit in regard he had his daughters conſent, and in regard the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reprehendeth it not, and that it might ſeem a Type of the militant Church ſubmitting her ſelf to martyrdom in honour of the victory of Chriſt, the fact of <hi>Jephte</hi> may be argued. But however <hi>Jephte</hi> his miſcarriage, in not breaking, but accompliſhing his raſh and imprudent vow, cannot (as aforeſaid) be a ſufficient Warrant for the <hi>Limited</hi> high Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to break his Oath or promiſe made with delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and according to prudence, that a People might be preſerved from ſlavery, oppreſſion, or meer Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government; ſo that he is bound by the tie of honeſty and fidelity to a ſtrict obſervation of his Rules and Limitations, nor ought he to exceed them, nor in any thing to violate them, unleſs he be releaſed of his Oath or Promiſe by the People, or their Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees, or by them enlarged touching his Rules and Limitations. <hi>All underſtanding men know, that a deliberate and prudent Oath or Promiſe ought to be kept.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168405:12"/>
               <head>OBSERVATION. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vpon the fourteenth Ground;</hi> in what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the ſubject may reſiſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>And upon the fifteenth Ground;</hi> wherein conſiſts the Power and Liberty of the ſubject.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN this place I muſt tell Mr. <hi>White,</hi> that he doth either of purpoſe, or miſtake, confound the Power of a <hi>Limited</hi> high Magiſtrate, and of an <hi>unlimited</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate; for in the places which I have quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſcope is touching a <hi>Limited</hi> high Magiſtrate, in other places he inſtanceth, or induceth the Power of an <hi>unlimited</hi> ſupream Magiſtrate, as in the twelfth Ground, page 98. where he ſaith; <hi>The next thing that occureth is the ſubjects fact by making this Truſt, and that is, that he hath made away all Power of judging and caring for the common good, farther than the eyes and hands of the Magiſtrate, his Truſtee, otherwiſe they have not made him ſupream Governour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I intend not to diſcourſe of ſuch an <hi>unlimited</hi> Magiſtrate, <hi>to whom</hi> the People, <hi>by making away all Power of judging and caring for the common good,</hi> have ſubmitted themſelves ſlaves, to ſtand to his Judgment, ſolid, or not ſolid, and to depend on his conſcience, or rather will, good, or bad: but my intent is to diſcourſe of a <hi>Limited</hi> Magiſtrate <hi>from whom</hi> the People <hi>have received the chief Power to their Truſtees of judging</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168405:12"/> 
                  <hi>and caring for the common good,</hi> and of the Peoples duty to ſuch a Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman ſaith (Ground 14. page 112.) <hi>Who ſhould ask me, if the Governour exacted for one time all the ſubject had, ſo there remained a Ground to work upon a new, and within a little time to live content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly; I ſhould be troubled to confeſs, it were a ſufficient injury to take up arms againſt him, becauſe I cannot judge which were the greater miſcheif to the ſubject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly I am no whit troubled to aver, that a <hi>Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> Governour, who ſhould deal ſo enormouſly with any People, <hi>as to exact all they had, leaving them onely a Ground to work upon a new,</hi> ought not onely to be by arms (if no other Remedy be left) diſplaced, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, but alſo puniſhed <hi>Romano more majorum:</hi> for he not onely violateth or breaketh his Promiſe or Oath, which obliged and tied him to his <hi>Limitations,</hi> but inhumanly trampleth upon the Rule of Nature it ſelf, to ſpoil thoſe whom he ought to protect. To <note place="margin">Even by the ſtrength of that Power which he ought to defend.</note> omit the Scenes of horrid Tyrants, <hi>Chriſtianus</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Denmark</hi> for oppreſſions, no way ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to what Mr. <hi>White</hi> hath ſtated, was expelled out of his Kingdom, and could never be admitted to the Government, albeit <hi>Charles</hi> the fift (his Brother in Law) and ſome other Princes laboured what they might for his reſtauration. For my part, I never read that any of the Eaſtern Monarchs did at any time ſo Tyrannize over the ſubjects, as <hi>at one time to axact all the ſubjects had;</hi> howbeit thoſe effeminate people, uſed to the yoak of ſlavery, do voluntarily or careleſly undergo the burden of Tyranny.</p>
               <p>Touching the clauſe; <hi>viz. So there remained a ground to work upon of new, and within a little time to</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168405:13"/> 
                  <hi>live contentedly;</hi> It is a Riddle above my reach, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive from what clouds ſuch contentedneſs ſhould drop, unleſs pains, and penury, inſtead of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and proſperity, ſhould be eſteemed contentedneſs; as amongſt the poor Peaſants in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Gentleman ſayes (page 114.) <hi>When evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently the Tyranny of the Governour is greater than the miſcheif hazarded (viz.</hi> of taking up arms againſt him) <hi>when ever this happeneth, be the material condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions what they will, the ſubject is free.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would know of Mr. <hi>White,</hi> or any Rational man, whether it were not better for the Subject to take up armes, than to ſuffer a Tyrant <hi>at one time to exact all the ſubject had,</hi> leaving onely <hi>a ground to work upon of new,</hi> which peradventure may be barely the ſpade and ground? If the Subject permit a Tyrant <hi>at one time,</hi> (or, I ſay, at ſeveral times) <hi>to exact all,</hi> he is acceſſary to his own wrong, but if he depoſe and ſeverely puniſh ſuch a Tyrant, he juſtly vindicateth himſelf according <note place="margin">Gen. 14. dictateth this: Alſo the Book of <hi>Judges.</hi>
                  </note> to his original or primitive Power <hi>in the force of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which giveth to every People power to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from any kind of ſlavery, to which they have not, or do not <hi>voluntarily</hi> ſubmit: Now it is in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>evident,</hi> that the Tyranny of the Governour <hi>in exacting all,</hi> is greater than the miſcheif, hazarded by the ſubject, in endeavouring <hi>by arms to preſerve all,</hi> by ſuffering the firſt, nothing but ſlavery can be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by hazarding the other, freedom may be hoped for, and if loſt, yet Rationally and nobly loſt: howbeit I think it very Rational to go prudently, and not raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to work, in ſo weighty a caſe.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>White</hi> ingeniouſly confeſſeth (page 119.) <hi>It is clear, there can be no queſtion of the neceſsity of the</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168405:13"/> 
                  <hi>reſiſtance; for they are ſuch</hi> (ſpeaking of the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a Tyrant) <hi>as do put the queſtion beyond all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity in the very conſcience of the Magiſtrate</hi> (he ſhould have done well to have added, if he have any) <hi>the objects bearing on the ſubject, in every ones particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, beyond denial and diſpute.</hi> Such a one, <hi>who put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his Subjects to ſuch extremities,</hi> Mr. <hi>White</hi> alſo (page 118.) jugdeth fit, <hi>to deſerve all the miſcheif that may light upon him for it:</hi> and withal concludeth that diſcourſe (page 120.) <hi>And therefore his either ignorance, or carleſneſs, or Tyranny, ought to be ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it be beyond all queſtion; or elſe the ſubiect muſt have patience for his own good, which is his aim in putting himſelf under Government.</hi> Now if <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> (which may peradventure be but miſtake) or <hi>careleſneſs</hi> (which may ſometimes be but confidence) ſeeming <hi>ſo evident</hi> to the apprehenſions of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as that <hi>they be beyond all queſtion,</hi> are Grounds (I will not ſay ſufficient) for the Subiect to reſiſt the Magiſtrate, certainly the Tyranny <hi>of exacting all the Subiect had,</hi> at one time, leaving onely <hi>a ground to work upon of new,</hi> (being a caſe more tranſcendent in <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary</hi> miſchief, than ignorance, or careleſneſs, which may ſometimes be <hi>involuntary)</hi> muſt needs be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ground for the ſubiect, not onely to reſiſt the Magiſtrate (if he reform not, and make reſtitution for <note place="margin">The Roman <hi>Caeſars,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Nero,</hi> had the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Senate, and the impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite conſent of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome,</hi> at leaſt wiſe <hi>a parte poſt.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch oppreſſion) but alſo ſeverely to puniſh him; which thing Mr. <hi>White</hi> needed not to have been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in his Judgment to have confeſſed.</p>
               <p>And now I think it not amiſs to declare who are Tyrants: whoſoever acquireth power or ſoveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>by meer force,</hi> without the <hi>explicite</hi> or <hi>implicite</hi> (which ſome call <hi>tacite)</hi> conſent of a Nation, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168405:14"/> People, is a Tyrant: formeer acquiſition of Power, or <hi>merum Imperium,</hi> doth not barely of it ſelf create any Right, no more than doth a forcible Entry, or Poſſeſſion unduly gotten. Alſo all and every Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Monarchical, Ariſtocratical, or Democratical, who <note place="margin">I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced touching <hi>Limited</hi> Tyrants, &amp; if <hi>unlimited</hi> Potentates may be Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>Limited</hi> Potentates muſt be Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants if they tranſgreſs their <hi>Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
                  </note> (albeit they have the Peoples conſent <hi>explicite,</hi> or <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite,</hi> without <hi>Limitation)</hi> do <hi>tranſgreſs the end of Government (which is the Peoples ſafety and welfare)</hi> are Tyrants; the Reaſon is, becauſe all Government is <hi>by the Rule of Reaſon</hi> intended for <hi>Protection and Preſervation,</hi> not any <hi>for deſtruction or deſolation;</hi> and therefore this is an uſual <hi>Maxim,</hi> viz. <hi>ubi nulla Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectio, nulla ſubiectio;</hi> the Reaſon is, becauſe <hi>the final cauſe or end</hi> of ſubiection (which is <hi>Protection)</hi> is wanting; to which end St. <hi>Paul</hi> pointeth at, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 6, <hi>Therefore,</hi> or <hi>to this end, pay ye Tribute,</hi> &amp;c. I think it convenient to define <hi>Protection,</hi> and <hi>Subiection,</hi> and from thence to deduce ſome Reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Protectio eſt Relatio Defenſiva ſuperiorum erga infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">That of 1 Pet. 2. 18. is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>froward</hi> Maſters Protecting and paying wages, or allowing mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Protection is a Defenſive Relation of Superiors towards Inferiors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Subiectio eſt Relatio ſubmiſsiva Inferiorum erga Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Subiection is a ſubmiſſive Relation of Inferiors towards Superiors.</p>
               <p>Hence it will follow, that the <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned</hi> are but as <hi>Relatum &amp; Correlatum:</hi> that the <hi>ſubmiſsive Relation</hi> of Rational Obedience ſuppoſeth the <hi>Defenſive Relation</hi> of Rational Juſtice: we ought <hi>Rationally</hi> (not blindly) to obey, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. we ought <hi>Rationally</hi> (not raſhly) to Judge, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 57. Hence it follows alſo, that no <hi>ſubmiſsive Relation</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168405:14"/> Rational obedience is due to ſuch Tyrants (if any ſuch Monſters be amongſt mankind) who at will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive their vaſſals of life, or take away from whom they pleaſe, what they pleaſe, when they pleaſe, <hi>ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrium;</hi> for ſuch do not defend, but deſtroy; nor can I be of opinion, that any People did at any time ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to, or rather enthral themſelves under ſuch Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants <hi>voluntarily,</hi> but of <hi>conſtraint,</hi> which if ſo, then are they Free (if able) to free themſelves; as I have formerly ſhewed.</p>
               <p>But whether or no any People have <hi>voluntarily</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved themſelves I ſhall not inſiſt upon: Howbeit I will inſtance the late Government of <hi>England,</hi> not <hi>ſo unlimited</hi> as ſome have ſuppoſed it, and would perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture have had it ſo, but exactly Regulated to the Rational end of Government, until Exorbitances, like briars, over-ſpread the Land. In <hi>England</hi> the King had the ſole power <hi>Juritenent,</hi> or of <hi>Law-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring,</hi> but not <hi>ſolely,</hi> for in the time of <hi>Parliaments</hi> they could ioyntly adminiſter Law, and Judge of matter of Fact, even as could the King: In <hi>England</hi> the King had onely a Joynt-power of <hi>Juredicent,</hi> or of <hi>Law-making,</hi> for without the <hi>Parliament</hi> the King could neither make, nor repeal Laws, nor <hi>(Legally)</hi> impoſe Taxes upon the People. <hi>Yet the leaving matters of great conſequence to the Reſolution of the governed Party, did not make them Governours</hi> (as Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſuppoſeth, Ground 15. pa. 127.) for the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Parliament</hi> were <hi>co-ordinate</hi> with the <hi>King</hi> in <hi>Law-making,</hi> and <hi>Law-adminiſtring</hi> at the times of their Seſſions; and in other things, and at other times <hi>ſubordinate</hi> to the King. Moreover in <hi>England</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King, nor Parliament (though united in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168405:15"/> could do three things: to wit;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>To deliver over the People of</hi> England <hi>to a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Government.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>To deliver over the National Benefit of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> England <hi>to a People diſtinct in Law and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To deprive the People of</hi> England <hi>of their own National Law.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>That is to ſay, to judge and determine <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> contrary to the Eſſence of any Law, as long as ſuch Law was <hi>in Being.</hi> For the Kingly and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary <note place="margin">Sacred Scripture is the written Rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>Law Poſitive</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Nulled</hi> or <hi>repealed, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> power united was but <hi>efficiently in Poſſe,</hi> not <hi>formally in Eſſe,</hi> above the Law, becauſe the Law obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all, even King and Parliament, until ſuch Law were by Parliament (being the Repreſentative Body of the Nation, and Truſtees of the People) <hi>nulled</hi> or <hi>altered.</hi> The Reaſon is, becauſe all Government ought to be <hi>Regular</hi> for the peoples ſafety, not any <hi>abſolutely,</hi> or <hi>meerly Arbitrary</hi> to their Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, if the Kingly and Parliamentary pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould have granted the <hi>Propriety</hi> of <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> meerly at their pleaſure, contrary to Law <hi>in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> albeit they ſhould therein have violated but the Right of one man <hi>Explicitely</hi> and <hi>Actually,</hi> yet they had therein violated the Right of all men in <hi>England Implicitely</hi> and <hi>Potentially,</hi> in regard all men had been ſubject to the like Danger. In ſuch caſe I ſhould have applied to the King and Parliament what Mr. <hi>White</hi> applieth to the Magiſtrate (Ground 15. page 123.) where he ſayes; <hi>So that in truth, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate firſt by his miſcarriages abdicateth himſelf from being a Magiſtrate, and becometh a Brigand and Robber,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168405:15"/> 
                  <hi>inſtead of a Defender; And the People, in way of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Preſervation of themſelves, make Reſiſtance againſt him.</hi> But Mr. <hi>White</hi> applieth this to a Magiſtrate, who ſhould wrong, or Tyrannize over a People in General; and ſeemeth to deny (page 129.) that any Reſiſtance may be made by a People to vindicate the wrongs of ſome Particulars; for he ſaith, <hi>If the wrong be done to Particulars, we ought to conſider, that acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal harms cannot be prevented neither in nature nor in humane affairs; and ſo are objects of pitty, rather than of hope to be amended, and to be tolerated rather, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the great good which is the common peace, than expoſe all to ſuch confuſion as muſt be, and ever hath been where the Government is, in part placed in unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not altogether of the Gentlemans opinion; for beſides the Rule of Humanity, the Tye of <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Amity</hi> obligeth a whole Nation to vindicate the wrongs of a few, even by arms) if no other Redreſs can be had) eſpecially when the wrongs done to ſome Particulars may manifeſtly ſeem to preſage the Ruine of all. I do not find, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had any ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al warrant from GOD to puniſh and ſuppreſs by Arms the <hi>Benjamites</hi> for not puniſhing ſuch as abomi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nably abuſed the <hi>Levites Wife or Condubine (Judges</hi> 19. &amp; 20.) yet for the wrong of one or two, the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> hazarded <hi>the good of common Peace,</hi> to do the good of Juſtice; and ſurely they did <hi>Rationally,</hi> for the good of Juſtice is to be preferred before the good of Peace; albeit Peace is highly to be eſteemed as a bleſſing from GOD, yet Juſtice is to be eſteemed as the Rule of GOD Regulating humane Affairs, and though not <hi>formally,</hi> yet <hi>finally omnis virtus;</hi> for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168405:16"/> Preſervation whereof men ought to hazard Peace or Tranquillity, Lives and Livelihoods: as for that <hi>of expoſing all to confuſion, &amp;c.</hi> it hath ſo happened when a giddy Multitude have raſhly attempted ſomewhat againſt their high Magiſtate, or ſuperior Rulers, but ſeldom, or never, when an whole Nation, or People, or the major, or a very conſiderable part of them, have <hi>prudently</hi> engaged againſt an over-lording Oppreſſor, or Oppreſſors, as in <hi>Switzerland</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now return to inſtance ſomewhat more touching the former Government of <hi>England,</hi> before I conclude the diſcourſe thereof.</p>
               <p>In <hi>England</hi> neither the King nor Parliament were (to ſpeak ſtrictly) the efficient cauſes of Laws <hi>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,</hi> but onely <hi>ſecundarily:</hi> The Reaſon is, becauſe the People tied the King by Oath <hi>to conſerve the juſt Laws which the Peogle ſhall chuſe,</hi> or (as ſome contend) <hi>have</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>England</hi> the People had a <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Innate</hi> power of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting</hi> and <hi>Intruſting Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives;</hi> The Kings Writ did only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the time and place, not give power, as ſomehave ſuppoſed, &amp; expreſſed.</note> 
                  <hi>choſen:</hi> The People alſo nominated, and, as it were, created their repreſentatives in Parliament; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were heretofore born by Deſcent to their Kingly Office, and ſo many times admitted thereunto before they took their ſolemn Oath, yet the People alwayes admitted them with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of their Oaths to be taken, and kept, or performed. I therefore make this Argument.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. All <hi>Power</hi> which did <hi>primarily</hi> oblige by Oath, and which did conſtitute Repreſentatives, was <hi>the primary Power of Laws,</hi> or <hi>of Law-making.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The People of <hi>England</hi> were the <hi>Power</hi> which did <hi>primarily</hi> oblige the King by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168405:16"/> Oath, and which did conſtitute Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. <note place="margin">Olim Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, (ut vocantur) a Populo electi fuerunt, ad denotandum Populi libere conſenſum erga Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſirſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos; hoc Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Therefore, the People of <hi>England</hi> were the <hi>primary Power of Laws,</hi> or <hi>of Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>major</hi> (touching the King) is manifeſt; for firſt, not any can oblige another by Oath, but ſuch as have ſome power over him; wherefore it was truly ſaid of an able Lawyer, that the King was <hi>ſingulis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, univerſis minor;</hi> for indeed the People are <hi>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,</hi> and <hi>intenſively</hi> above any Kingly Power in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hanc rerum etiam Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura denotat, de Mathiae, Acts</hi> 1. <hi>de ſeptem Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conis, Acts</hi> 6.</note> of the end of Government, which is <hi>ſalus Populi,</hi> and therefore to be preferred before <hi>Majeſtas Imperii.</hi> Secondly, the Kingly Oath was <hi>in nature of Contract,</hi> which obligeth between Contractor and Contracted. Both <hi>major</hi> and <hi>minor</hi> are alſo manifeſt (touching the Repreſentatives) it being evidently known by the Peoples former Indentures to their Truſtees.</p>
               <p>To apply what I have written touching the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Government of <hi>England;</hi> I ſay, where ſuch Government or the like doth continue, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was State-holder in <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp;c. but not wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, ſo were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſome Princes, or Princely Lords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt the <hi>Switzers.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Switzerland,</hi> &amp;c. (albeit thoſe People ſeldom <hi>pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiate</hi> their Truſtees without Limitations) the Governours and Truſtees <hi>abdicate</hi> themſelves from the Government and Truſt repoſed in them by the People, and are ſubject to their <hi>primary</hi> power al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>intended</hi> and <hi>reſerved</hi> for their preſervation: <hi>for every Free man hath a natural innate power in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of himſelf, and All united have a national innate power in All of All.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not take upon me to preſcribe Rules of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but onely ſay, that that Government is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168405:17"/> beſt for any people, to which the people will willingly ſubmit, and which they may, or have power to reform <hi>(by their Truſtees or Delegates)</hi> if it become greivous or burthenſome unto them.</p>
               <p>And ſo far Mr. <hi>White</hi> ſeemeth to aſſent (Ground 1. page 7.) ſaying, <hi>Men are not wont to repine often at what themſelves chuſe and judge beſt for themſelves; eſpecially if, even after the action performed, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the attempt failed, yet the ſubject re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſatisfied, that it was beſt for him, in thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, to do what he did.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh that all Governours, <hi>unlimited</hi> as well as <hi>limited,</hi> would conſider this, not prefering their own ſelf-ends, or greatneſs, before the Peoples <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imbracing</hi> Good. <hi>Jamque opus exegi.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>WILL. BALL.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
